(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-08-31T05:12:59.284850",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
梅雨ライブ
今宵はきっと雨が降る
Rainy Season Live
Tonight, it will surely rain
今宵はきっと
Tonight, surely...
雨が降る
it will rain.
6月 水無月
June
梅雨
Rainy Season
雨
Rain
猫又おかゆ
Nekomata Okayu
笑えないわ 「不幸になった」ってどの口が言うのだろう
It's laughable to say, "I became unfortunate,"
Whose mouth could possibly say that?
もう何回 誤魔化している
How many times have I glossed it over,
その指で遊んでる
playing with it on my fingertips?
ふざけないで 被害者ぶったって
Even if you act like a victim, playing the fool,
何も変わりはしないのに 夜は更けてく おやすみ
nothing changes at all, so goodnight.
だから 相対するのは夜が明けてから
That's why meeting face-to-face
has to wait until after dawn.
ほらね 今日は眠るのさ
So come on, today we'll sleep.
そして こんな言葉に意味などはないから
And because words like that have no meaning,
気にしないで 目を閉じて
don't mind them and close your eyes.
傷が付いて 変わっていった程度ものと言うのでしょう
Wound up and changed to some degree,
もう何回 繰り返してる その胸で眠ってる
I'm sleeping against that chest again,
不意に吐いた 「嫌いじゃないよ」って その言葉で揺れるのに
blurting out unthinkingly, "I don't hate it,"
そうやって 目を伏せるのは 何故
yet why do I cast my eyes down?
曖昧になるのは 嘘に怯えるから
Becoming ambiguous because I fear the lie,
またね 遠く灯が揺れる
once again, distant lights flicker.
ここで 愛情を問うには あまりに遅いから
It's far too late to question affection here,
聞かなかったことにしよう
let's just pretend I never heard it.
青になって熟れる様な 赤になって枯れる様な
Like turning blue and ripening,
or turning red and withering away,
拙い想いだけ 募ってしまって仕方がないんだよ
these clumsy feelings just overflow, and I can't help it.
だから 相対するのは夜が明けてから
That's why meeting face-to-face has to wait until after dawn.
ほらね 今日は眠るのさ
So come on, today we'll sleep.
そして あんな言葉も優しさと言うから
And because even those words are called kindness,
触れる様な虚しさが 残る
a palpable emptiness remains...
くしゃくしゃになった診察券を持って
Holding a crumpled-up clinic receipt,
簡単な想像に日々を使っている
I spend my days on simple imaginations.
単調な風景に ふと眠くなって
Suddenly growing sleepy amidst the monotonous scenery,
回送列車に揺られ動いている
I'm being swayed by a deadhead train.
看板の照明が後ろめたくなって
The lighting of the sign became a blur behind me,
The light from the billboard made me feel so guilty,
目を落とした先で笑っていた
and where I cast my eyes, someone was smiling.
通りを抜けて路地裏の方で 屈託もなく笑っていた
Passing through the street into a back alleyway, they laughed so carelessly.
映画の上映はとうに終わっている
The movie screening's finished by now, long ago.
叱責の記憶がやげに響くから
The memories of censure echo so vividly in my mind.
できれば遠くに行かないでくれ
If possible, please don't go too far away.
できるなら痛くしないで
If you can, please don't cause me pain.
構わないで 離れていて
Don't pay me any heed, just stay away from me.
軋轢にきゅっと目をつむって
Tightly shutting your eyes against all this friction,
報わないで 話をして
don't expect a return, just talk to me.
窓越しにじっと目を合わせて
Look at me steadily through the windowpane.
退廃に暮れた劇場の隅で
In the corner of a theater lost in decadence,
眠らなかったはずが眠っている
although I'm supposed to be insomniac, I'm nodding off.
アラベスクには触れなかったんだ
I was unable to touch the arabesque.
火がついたように 街が光った
It was like a fire, so bright the streets lit up.
無頓着なあの子が 傘を差したら
When that careless girl opened up her umbrella,
それで救われるくらい単純でしょ
it's simple enough to be saved by that, right?
左手の指輪 右手に隠して 戸惑ってるふうにしてた
Hiding my left-hand ring in my right, putting on a confused act.
捜さないで いつの間にか
Don't search for me, before you even realize
消えたことに気づく距離ならば
that I've vanished into the distance,
許さないで 最初だけは
don't forgive me, at least not at first,
悲しくもないはずにしたくて
wanting to make it seem like there's nothing to mourn.
構わないで 離れていて
Don't pay me any heed, just stay away from me.
軋轢にきゅっと目をつむって
Tightly shutting your eyes against all this friction,
報わないで 話をして
don't expect a return, just talk to me.
窓越しにじっと目を合わせて
Look at me steadily through the windowpane.
眠らないで 言葉にして
Don't fall asleep, put it into words.
照らした光に目を細めて
Squinting your eyes against the shining light.
笑わないで 君に咲いた執着よ、
Don't laugh at me, this obsession that bloomed in you—
僕を飲み込んでくれ
please swallow me whole.
みんなー！やっほー！
Everyone! Yoo-hoo!
僕が言った通り 今日雨降ったでしょ？
Just like I said, it rained today, right?
今日はね、この、傘とか、
Today, you know, things like this umbrella...
みんなちょっと気づいてると思うけど、
I think you all might have noticed,
この足元にある長靴！
but these rain boots at my feet!
これすごくない？
Aren't these amazing?
これは、今日雨が降るだろうからって、長靴を用意してくれたんだよ。
They prepared these rain boots because they knew it'd rain today.
これすごくない？ちゃんとほら、猫のさ、このバッチみたいなのに白いリボンがついてて、
Aren't they cool? See, they have a cat badge-like thing with a white ribbon,
で、なんかこう可愛い紫色のかわいい長靴になってるんだよ。
and they're cute, purple rain boots!
もともとね、黄色い靴を履いてたから、
I originally wore yellow shoes,
なんかすごいでしょう？全体、全体の紫色感がね、すごい増えてて、
so isn't this amazing? The overall purple vibe has increased so much!
かわいいんだよー！
It's so cute!
ねこの傘もね、これすごいんでしょ？開けたり閉めたりできるんだよ。
The cat umbrella too—isn't this amazing? You can open and close it.
オープン！ほら！
Open! Look!
ほら傘すご、このね、お水でね、濡れてるんだよ傘も。すごいよね！
Look at the umbrella, it's wet with water. Isn't that amazing?
みんなとね、相合い傘しようと思えばね、できるんだよ。ほら！
You know, if you wanted to share an umbrella with me, you could. Look!
こうかな？こっちの方にほら、みんなも入れるし、
Like this? Over here, everyone can fit,
ねこいぬを 守るボクみたいな演出をね、感じる事ができます。
You get this vibe... like I'm protecting a cat-dog.
いやでも今日はね、あのこれからまだまだたくさん雨がね、止みそうにないので、
Well, but today... um, since it doesn't look like the rain is going to stop anytime soon tonight,
その雨がやまない今夜は、ボクの歌をたくさん聴いてもらえればいいなと思っています。
I hope you'll listen to a lot of my songs tonight while the rain keeps falling.
では、次の曲いきたいと思います。
Now then, let's go to the next song.
あー、あ、はい。なんかね、運営さんミスっちゃったんだって。
Ah, ah, yes. Apparently, management made a mistake.
次はお屋上みたいなんで、移動するからちょっと待っててね。
The next one is like a rooftop, so I'm going to move there, please wait a bit.
次の曲、聴いてください。プロトディスコ。
Please listen to the next song: Proto Disco.
おんなじだけ夢を見てる滑稽さに
In the absurdity of dreaming the exact same dreams,
違う言葉を今だ待ち続けている
I am still waiting for a different set of words.
今しがた終わるはずだった想像に
Into the imagination that should have ended just now,
延命処置を続けてまだ息を注ぐ
I keep providing life support and continue to breathe life into it.
代わりの利く感動を焼き増しのドラマチックをあなたへあなたへ
To you, to you—with a reusable excitement, a reprinted dramatic flare,
語り得ぬさいはての奥を無理矢理繋ぎ
Forcibly connecting the ineffable, furthest depths,
奪わないでなくさないでそれから どうかもっともっと嫌って際限なんか奪って
Don't take it away, don't lose it, and then... Please hate me more and more, steal all limits,
衝動なんかもどうだっていい 崇める意味が溢れる前に オリジナルの地獄に落ちて
I don't care about impulses either. Before the meaning of worship overflows, fall into your original hell.
どうかもっともっと祈って這いつくばって祈って 偶像なんか追い縋っていて
Please pray more and more, crawl and pray, chasing after idols,
失っていて墜落していて 作り上げた虚無に胡坐をかいている
Losing everything, crashing down, sitting complacently on the emptiness we built.
カラカラの脳味噌を絞り続けている
Squeezing my parched brains dry,
踊らされることをまだ自覚している
Still aware that I am being made to dance.
安全な街の中で君が見据えているものは あたしだあたしだ
In this safe city, what you are gazing at is me, it is me.
吐き出し捨てていくことさえ咎められなくて 笑わないで厭わないで歪んで
Even spitting things out isn't condemned; don't smile, don't hate it, just distort.
どうかもっともっと惑ってキャッチーを奪って 救援なんか来なくてもいい
Please get more and more lost, steal the catchy tunes, rescue doesn't even need to come,
忘れるなんて出来ないくらい脳髄にちゃんと擦り込んで
Imprint it deep into my brain so I can never forget it.
どうかもっともっと描いて空想なんて拭って 盲信ばっかもう窮屈なの
Please draw more and more, wipe away mere fantasies—blind faith is already too stifling.
油を差して火を灯して錆びついている言語に血を通してみて
Oil it, light a fire, and try breathing life into rusted language.
明快な回答は無く こんな歌だって陳腐なんだ
With no clear answer, even a song like this is cliché.
再来の審議ばっかで まだ踊り足りないの！
With nothing but repeated deliberations, I'm still not done dancing!
どうかもっともっと嫌って際限なんか奪って 衝動なんかもどうだっていい
Please hate me more and more, steal all limits, I don't care about impulses either.
崇める意味が溢れる前に
Before the meaning of worship overflows...
Before the meaning to worship overflows,
オリジナルの地獄に落ちて
fall into the original hell.
どうかもっともっと描いて後悔なんてしないで
Please draw more and more, and don't have any regrets.
雑音なんて消えてしまえ
May all the noise just disappear.
浪費している言葉で呼ばれて
Call me with wasted words,
終わりのない温度で焼き尽くして 震わせてみてよ
burn me to ashes with endless warmth and make me tremble!
はい。というわけで、プロトディスコでした。
Yes. So that was "Proto Disco".
えー、一番最初名誉から始まって、え、ブラジル、そしてプロトディスコまで来たんですけど、
Um, it started with "Meiyo", then Brazil, and came all the way to "Proto Disco".
ま、ここまで物は、ま、ちょっとロックな感じだけど、少し、ま、しっとりというか、しっとりかっこいい感じの曲で、え、終わったんですけど、
Up to here, the songs have been kind of rock-style, but also a bit mellow and cool, and they've ended.
次の曲は、ま、結構ね、激しく雨降ってるので、激しい感じの曲にも挑戦していこうかなと思ってます。
For the next song, since it's raining pretty hard, I thought I'd take on a more intense kind of song.
おーい！
Hey there!
みんなどこにいるんだろ？あっちかな？あっちかな？
Where is everyone? Over there? Or over there?
これからもね、ちょっとかっこいい僕をみんなに見せていければなと思うので、次の曲行きたいと思います。
I want to keep showing you all my cool side moving forward, so I'd like to move on to the next song.
では、聞いてください。アンドロメダだ！アンドロメダだ！
Now, please listen. Andromeda! Andromeda!
ワレワレは宇宙人だ
We are aliens,
校舎の裏からコンタクト
making contact from behind the school building.
プラズマはあなた狙う
Plasma aims at you,
届ける思いは超電波
our delivered feelings are super electromagnetic waves.
放課後の奇跡体験
This after-school miraculous experience,
感じているのギャラクシー
I'm feeling the galaxy.
観測はあなた次第
Observation depends on you,
渦巻く想いは恋心
swirling feelings are a heart in love.
アンドロメダアンドロメダ 答えておくれ
Andromeda, Andromeda, please answer me.
あなたとわたし 永久に逢えないの
You and I can never meet for eternity.
アンドロメダアンドロメダ 気づいておくれ
Andromeda, Andromeda, please notice me.
彼方の宇宙であなたに恋してる
I'm in love with you in a distant universe.
パルラパルラパルラッタッタラ
Parula parula parula ttattara!
裏山で大放電 赤色光ったエレキテル
A massive discharge behind the mountain, an elekitel shining red.
怪音がとおくで響く 夜中の3時に近所迷惑
A strange sound echoes far away, disturbing the neighborhood at 3 a.m.
屋上の秘密クラブ 感じてほしいのミステリー
The secret rooftop club wants you to feel this mystery.
光線はあなた狙う 密かに打ちぬくの恋心
A light beam aims at you, secretly shooting through your heart of love.
アンドロメダアンドロメダ 答えておくれ
Andromeda, Andromeda, please answer me.
あなたとわたし 永久に逢えないの
You and I can never meet for eternity.
アンドロメダアンドロメダ 忘れておくれ
Andromeda, Andromeda, please forget me.
あなたと宇宙は本当によく似てる
You and the universe are really so much alike.
パルラパルラパルラッタッタラ
Parula parula parula ttattara!
アンドロメダアンドロメダ でした。
That was "Andromeda".
えっと、雨の音をずっと聞いてる時ってさ、どんな歌聴きたくなる？
Um, when you're listening to the sound of rain for a long time, what kind of songs do you feel like listening to?
僕は今回雨の中でライブをするって決まった時には
When it was decided that I'd be doing a live stream in the rain this time,
やっぱ雨が降ってるからちょっとこうクールな感じもいいなって思ってたんだけど
I thought it'd be cool since it's raining, you know?
でもやっぱり見てるみんなが少しね胸の奥が熱くなるような曲を選びたいなって思ったので
But I wanted to pick songs that would warm everyone's hearts watching,
今回はちょっとクールだけど聞いてると少しなんか胸の奥が熱くなるような曲をたくさん歌っていこうと思ってます
so this time, even though they're cool, I'm planning to sing lots of songs that warm your heart a bit.
ああじゃあそろそろ次の曲なんだけど
Ah, well, it's almost time for the next song, but...
あそうだ歌のイメージに合わせてどうしてみよっか
Ah, that's right. Let's think about how to match it to the song's image!
ラララララ…
La la la...
今更なんにも言わないが お前の態度が気に食わぬ
I won't say anything now, but your attitude pisses me off.
気配上手で聞き上手 他言無用もお手の物
Good at hiding presence and listening, keeping secrets is a breeze,
おまけに突飛な輩にも 小慣れた手つきで擬態処理
and handling bizarre types with practiced ease.
聖人君子の生き写し 不平不満も漏らさずに
The spitting image of a saint, without uttering a single complaint.
誰彼皆々お前らの 味方になるけれど
You become an ally to anyone and everyone, but...
それでもアタシは許さない 認めない
Even so, I won't forgive you. I won't acknowledge you.
人目避けて行こうぜ ラララララ…
Let's go avoiding people's eyes, la la la...
死のみぞ一斉送信 ラララララ…
Simultaneous broadcast of death alone, la la la...
嫉妬で駆けて行こうぜ ラララララ…
Let's run with jealousy, la la la...
乳飲子一転攻勢 ラララララ…
A sudden counterattack by an infant, la la la...
アタシが善とは思わぬが お前が善などヘドが出る
I don't think I'm good, but you calling yourself good makes me want to puke.
とはいえ現世の目は明らか 自問自答で夜は暮れる
That said, the world's eyes are clear; nights pass in self-questioning.
理屈や倫理や常套句 はたまた論拠さえ
Logic, ethics, clichés, or even the basis of argument...
アタシの前では通じない 聞こえない 意味を殺してしまえよ
they don't work in front of me, I can't hear them—kill their meaning!
好きに狂ってしまえよ ラララララ…
Go crazy as you like, la la la...
いつも呪って歌うよ ラララララ…
I always sing with a curse, la la la...
頬を通って伝うよ ラララララ…
Streaming down my cheeks, la la la...
御託に酔っておられますが さしずめあんたも個人主義
You're drunk on your preachy talk, but you're also an individualist.
敵無く生きてく事なんざ 所詮お前には無理なのさ
Living without enemies is ultimately impossible for you.
人目避けて行こうぜ ラララララ…
Let's go avoiding people's eyes, la la la...
死のみぞ一斉送信 ラララララ…
Simultaneous broadcast of death alone, la la la...
嫉妬で駆けて行こうぜ ラララララ…
Let's run with jealousy, la la la...
乳飲子一転攻勢 ラララララ…
A sudden counterattack by an infant, la la la...
ということで、邪魔、いかがだったでしょうか。
And that was "Jama". How was it?
やっぱちょっとね、こうダークでかっこいい感じの曲だから、ま、こういうね、天気の日だからこそなんか歌いたいなっていう気持ちになったんだよね。
Since it's a cool, dark song, it made me want to sing it precisely because of this kind of weather.
なんか天気良くない日の方が、そういうダークな曲聞きたいなっていう気持ちになるんだけど、みんなはどうかな？
I feel like on days with bad weather, I want to listen to dark songs like that. How about everyone else?
あでも天気悪いから逆になんだろうな、こう、すごい元気が
Ah, but because the weather is bad, conversely, like...
もしかしたら、そういう曲聴きたいみたいなのもあるかもしれないよね。
Maybe some of you want to hear that kind of song, right?
ちなみに、この曲は、この「ジャマ」という曲はね、ダークなかっこいい感じだったから、まあ明るいステージとかでね、こう歌ってもいいなと思ったんだけど、
By the way, this song, "Jama," had such a dark and cool vibe, so I thought it'd be nice to sing it on a bright stage too, but...
やっぱ今日はこういうさ、こう屋上でさ、天気も悪くてさ、こういう時にこそやっぱ「ジャマ」を歌いたいっしょって僕は思ったんだよね。
But today, with weather like this on a rooftop, in times like this, I felt like I really wanted to sing "Jama."
なんかさ、今さ、運営さんからさ、「おかゆさんなんか手の振りとかこういうなんか、これ何て言うの？書作って言うのかな？書作？みたいなのが」なんか超よかったよって今褒められたんだけど。
Just now, management told me, "Okayu-san, your hand gestures and things like that—what do you call it? Shosaku? Like shosa?" They praised me, saying it was super good.
なんか、意識して聞いてることあるんですかって聞かれたけどさ、別になんですけどうふふふ。
They asked, "Is there anything you do consciously?" But not really, hehehe.
普段の、普段の美しさなんですけど。ふふっ。
It's just my usual, everyday beauty. Heh.
やっぱ普段はね、骨組みの時とかだとさ、こう手のなんか、こういう動きとかはさ、わかんないからさ。
I mean, normally, when it's just the skeleton model, I don't know what hand movements to make, so...
で、僕普段からこうやってなんか、こう潤わしてんだよね、手の動きがね。ふふっ。
So normally I make my hand movements look all smooth and hydrated, you know. Heh.
まあ、続き、まだまだね、続きますんで、こういうなんか動きなんかもね、注目してもらえればなと思います。ふふっ。
Well, it continues for a while, so I hope you'll pay attention to movements like these too. Heh.
運営さん褒めてくれてありがと。なんか意外なとこ褒められてびっくりなんだけど。
Thanks to management for the praise. I'm surprised to be praised in such an unexpected place though.
まあ、ちょっとね、なんかいっぱい歌ってきてちょっと疲れたから、座るとこ探そうかな。
Well, you know, having sung a lot, I'm a bit tired, so maybe I'll look for a place to sit down.
ああ、高いところってさ、なんかいいよね。看板とか車の明かりがさ、雨でキラキラって光ってて、
Ah, high places are kind of nice, aren't they? Signs and car lights shining sparklingly in the rain...
見てて飽きないんだあ。そうそう、高いところから街を見下ろしてる感じの曲を思い出したんだ。
I never get tired of watching. That's right, it reminded me of a song about looking down at the city from high up.
聞いてくれる？
Will you listen?
エゴの満場 理性の冷凍
A full house of ego, frozen reason,
あてのない最前線にどうして
why are we on a destinationless front line?
僕らは希望持って 恐れては叫んだ 無知の彼は僕の頭上
We held hope, feared and screamed; the ignorant one is right above my head.
如何せんアイロニー 告げてタイトに 栄誉なんて案外ノリ
Somehow irony, telling it tightly, glory is surprisingly casual.
変わってくランデブー 日々脱んでく
Changing rendezvous, shedding days one by one,
不甲斐ない夢はもう十分です
I've had enough of pathetic dreams.
大乱戦のオーダーメイド やった者勝ちに躊躇
A free-for-all custom-made, hesitating to the victors,
捨てされ左脳も意地も 類のない有頂天へと 突いて上がれ少年Aよ
discarding left brain and pride alike, pierce up to unprecedented ecstasy, boy A.
稀代の未来を掲げるくらいの
Enough to hold up a rare future,
盲点の発想 本末は転倒
a blind spot of an idea, ends inverted,
正解のない矛盾の向こうに
beyond the contradiction with no correct answer.
僕らは持論持って もがいては投げた 無垢な心情じゃ1の二乗
We held our theories, struggled and cast them away; with innocent feelings, it's 1 squared.
如何せんアイロニー 告げてタイトに 不滅なんて安牌のみ
Somehow irony, telling it tightly, immortality is just the safe bet.
いざ行かん我がメロス 寝ずのエンドレス
Now let's go, my Melos, sleepless endless,
くだらない夢にまた踊っています
dancing once again in a worthless dream.
等身大の自己嫌悪 抱いて綴れ「こうでいたい」と
Embracing life-sized self-hatred, spelling out "I want to be like this,"
附属に富豪も飢えも 酸いも甘いも中の下で 満足なんて宙の上で
appendices, the rich, and hunger too; sour and sweet, down in the middle-low, satisfaction up in the sky.
次の次も報われはないの?
Will the next time and the time after not be rewarded either?
oh oh oh oh 二兎追う者のみ
oh oh oh oh only those who chase two hares,
oh oh oh oh 目には手を
oh oh oh oh hands to the eyes,
oh oh oh oh 笑う門に来る事変よ
oh oh oh oh incident coming to the gate of smiles!
向いてないと杭を打って ついてないと賽を置いた
Hammering the stake saying "you're not cut out for it," placing the die saying "you're out of luck."
向いてないと杭を打って
Driving a stake because I'm not cut out for it,
ついてないと賽を置いた
rolling the dice because I'm out of luck.
目覚めればまた藍色に
When I wake up, it's indigo again,
絶え間ないが届かないのは嫌なんだ
I hate it when the ceaseless things don't reach me.
大乱戦のオーダーメイド
A custom-made chaotic battle,
やった者勝ちの名誉
glory goes to whoever takes action.
踊れ恐れを超えて
Dance, overcoming fear,
悔いはないと心臓売った勝算なんてない
with no regrets I sold my heart, with no odds of success—
まだまだ僕は
I'm still...
如何せん陰路に告げて対等に
Somehow telling the dark path to be equal,
来世で会えたら 限りないこの浮世に笑おう
If we meet in the next life, let's laugh in this boundless floating world.
銃を持って憂いを放って時代を露わに
Holding a gun, releasing my sorrow, exposing the era.
ああ、このビルの下に良さそうな場所発見！
Ah, I found a good-looking spot under this building!
あそこで歌ったら超楽しそうじゃん。
It'd be super fun to sing over there.
おにぎりゃーのみんな、ちょっと移動してもいい？
Onigirya everyone, do you mind if we move a bit?
あ、いいだね。
Ah, sounds good.
よし！
Alright!
じゃあ、おっけーみたいだから移動するぞー！
Okay, looks like it's okay, so we're moving!
おー！いいじゃんいいじゃん、この雰囲気。
Oh! This atmosphere is great, really great.
はあ、とりあえず今日はここまでたくさん歌ってきたけどさ、みんなどうだった？
Whew, anyway, I've sung a lot up to now today, how was it everyone?
僕はね、こんなに土砂降りの中で気持ちよく歌を歌える機会ってあんまりないからさ、
I rarely get the chance to sing so comfortably in such a downpour, so...
すごい貴重な機会だったし、めっっちゃめちゃ楽しかった！
It was such a precious opportunity, and super, super fun!
たまにはさ、外でね、思いっきり歌を歌うのもいいなって思ったよ。
I thought it'd be nice to sing my heart out outside once in a while.
僕引きこもりだからさ、そんなに外に行かないんだけどさ。
I'm a shut-in, so I don't go outside that much.
こういう日も、まああってもいいかなって思ったし、少し雨が好きになったかな。
I felt like having days like this is fine too, and I've come to like the rain a little.
今まではね、なんか雨って自分が外に出る機会があると、あんまり、なんか降ってると傘差すのもめんどくさいしやだなあって思ってたんだけどさ、まあ、こういう日があってもいいかなってちょっと思えるきっかけになったかな。
Up until now, whenever I had to go outside in the rain, I thought it was annoying to put up an umbrella and hated it, but maybe this became an opportunity to think that days like this aren't so bad.
あとはさ、この傘！傘すごいよね、やっぱりさ。このビニール傘と長靴、運営さんにね、作ってもらったんだけどさ、何度見付けてもさ、すごくない？これ。
And also, this umbrella! This umbrella is amazing, isn't it? This vinyl umbrella and rain boots were made for me by management, but no matter how many times I see them, aren't they amazing?
ほら見て見て！ほら濡れてんのいっぱい！
Look, look! Look how wet they are all over!
これからね、この運営さんに貰った傘を使って、いっぱいね、雨の日もお出かけしようって思ったよ。
From now on, using this umbrella given by management, I want to go out a lot even on rainy days.
ということで、ここまでいっぱい歌ったり喋ったりしてきましたけど、いよいよ、まもなくみんなあれが近づいているということでね、最後は2曲連続で歌わせていただこうと思います。
So, up to now we've sung and talked a lot, but finally, since that thing is approaching soon, I'd like to sing two songs consecutively for the end.
それでは聴いてください、バレリーコ。
Now then, please listen to Valerieco.
純情少女と勘違いされて
Mistaken for a pure-hearted girl,
全校男子に狙われた
targeted by all the boys in school.
あぁ初体験
Ah, my first experience
世にも恐ろし大出血乗り越え 恥ずべきものはなし
overcoming the world's most terrifying massive bloodshed—nothing to be ashamed of!
朱いリボンヒラヒラさせて
Letting my red ribbon flutter,
バイバイ プリマの放課後だ
bye-bye, it's the prima's after-school hours.
あぁ青春さん 汗と涙でベタベタになってなんか大変そうですね
Ah, youth-san, you're all sticky with sweat and tears, looks like it's pretty tough, huh?
ゆりり揺れるジャンパースカート
The loosely swaying jumper skirt,
ひっそり覗くスラックス
slacks peeking out stealthily.
目と目をあわせて戸惑うふりした 校内男女の関係
The relationship of school boys and girls who made eye contact and pretended to be flustered.
ねぇ ディン・ディン・ダン さあ踊りましょう
Hey, ding-ding-dong, come on, let's dance,
じょうずに飛び跳ねて エッサホイサ
jumping skillfully, essahoisah!
劣等感 ほら恥ずかしい それも人生だ
Inferiority complex, look how embarrassing—that's life too!
ねぇ ディン・ディン・ダン さあ踊りましょう
Hey, ding-ding-dong, come on, let's dance,
もっともっと激しく エッサホイサ
even more fiercely, essahoisah!
絶頂感 ほら最後まで面倒みてあげる
Peak sensation, look, I'll take care of you till the very end!
うわばきでシャル・ウィ・ダンス
Shall we dance in indoor shoes?
With indoor shoes, shall we dance?
先輩どうしてあの子がいんの 私の方がよい子でしょ
Senpai, why is that girl with you? Don't you think I'm a much better girl?
ぁ 奇々怪々 邪魔する猫はしししし すぐに踵を返しなさい
Ah, how peculiar! Pesky cats should shoo, shoo, shoo—turn right back around and leave!
ふわり香るリップクリーム じっとり濡れたセミロング
A sweetly scented lip cream, slightly damp, shoulder-length hair.
教師の言葉もひぐらしの声も聞こえない男女の関係
A relationship between a man and woman where neither teacher's words nor cicadas can be heard.
ねぇ ディン・ディン・ダン さあ踊りましょう
Hey, ding, ding, dong, now let's dance!
じょうずに飛び跳ねて エッサホイサ
Skillfully hopping and jumping, hetsahoy-sa!
劣等感 ほら恥ずかしい それも人生だ
Inferiority complex, look how embarrassing, but that's life too.
ねぇ 後悔はどこにあるのか 九回転のピルエット
Hey, where is the regret? Nine pirouettes.
トゥシューズぬいだ素足の歪な叫び 「…もう限界だ」
The distorted screams of bare feet with toe shoes off... "I've had enough."
ねぇ 先輩どうして泣いてるの? 一緒にアン・ドゥ・トロワして
Hey Senpai, why are you crying? Let's do un, deux, trois together.
マスカレード? どちらにするの? オデット? オディール?
Masquerade? Which will it be? Odette? Odile?
ねぇ ディン・ディン・ダン さあ踊りましょう
Hey, ding, ding, dong, now let's dance!
じょうずに飛び跳ねて エッサホイサ
Skillfully hopping and jumping, hetsahoy-sa!
劣等感 ほら恥ずかしい それも人生だ
Inferiority complex, look how embarrassing, but that's life too.
ねぇ グッバイ最後に踊りましょう
Hey, goodbye, let's dance for the last time.
もっともっと激しく エッサホイサ
Even more intensely, hetsahoy-sa!
絶頂感 今この瞬間 すべて完璧だ
Ecstasy, right this moment, everything is perfect.
うわばきでシャル・ウィ・ダンス
With indoor shoes, shall we dance?
最後の曲 聞いてください
Please listen to the final song.
ラストリゾート
Last Resort.
くしゃくしゃの頭の中で考えている
I'm thinking inside this messy head of mine.
十四時過ぎに開いた目がぼやけてる
The eyes I opened just past 2 PM are blurry.
唖呼またやって来た今日に舌打ちをして 始まる僕の最終演目
Clicking my tongue at today that has come once again, my final act begins.
四十二度溜息とスモーク アリンスー切れてたんだ 洗濯も溜まってたんだ
42-degree sigh and smoke, I ran out of rinse, and my laundry was piling up.
まあもういいか 狭くなったベランダの様だ ゴミ溜めの様だ それが僕だった
Well, whatever. It was like a narrowed veranda, like a pile of trash. That was me.
さあ何処までだって行こうか 唖呼此処までだって笑った
Now, let's go anywhere. Ah, I laughed, saying up to here.
逃げ場の無い世界で逃避行 恐れは無いもう無いな 歩き疲れたところで終わりにしようか
An escapade in a world with nowhere to run, there's no fear, none left. Shall we end it where we got tired of walking?
愛して堪らないからって 飼い馴らし過ぎてぎゅっと 手を繋いだままの怠惰が
Saying "because I love you so much I can't bear it," the laziness of holding hands while being too tamed...
こっちを見て笑った こんなもんと何度も笑った 憐れむ様な遠い目で
Looked at me and laughed, laughed many times saying "that's just how it is," with a distant, pitying gaze.
さあ何処までだって行こうか 唖呼此処までだって分かった
Now, let's go anywhere. Ah, I understood up to here.
行き場の無い世界に花束を 何でもいいもういいよ 見渡す限り僕だけ置き去りみたいだ
Offering a bouquet to a world with nowhere to go, anything is fine, it's fine now. As far as the eye can see, it seems I alone have been left behind.
嗚呼 散々だって嘆いた
Ah, lamenting that it's all a mess,
もう何回だって憂いた
grieving over and over again.
宛名の無い助けは届かずに
Unaddressed help fails to reach anyone,
何にも無いよもう無いよ
there's nothing left, no, nothing at all.
殴り連たねた言葉と終わりに行こうか
Shall we head to the end with these harsh words?
嗚呼 これでよかったんだって
Ah, chanting over and over,
そう何度も唱えて
"This was for the best,"
掴めずに消えてゆくユートピア
a utopia slipping away and fading,
あの時きっとねえきっと
surely, surely back then...
引き返すには少しだけ遅過ぎたようだ
It seems a bit too late to turn back now.
終わりを告げた
Declaring the end,
綺麗な日だった
it was a beautiful day.